Guide to the Peter J. Gay Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Peter J. Gay papers
1845-2015
MS 2034
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
15.5
(41 boxes)
The papers document the research, writings, teaching, and personal life of cultural historian Peter J. Gay. The papers consist of research and teaching files, writings, correspondence, photographs and slides, and personal papers. An extensive part of his research files is the work he completed on Sigmund Freud while writing Sigmund Freud: A Life for Our Time (1998). Gay's writing files contain more of his later articles, book manuscripts, and lectures than his earlier works and include drafts of three of his books: My German Question (1998), Modernism: The Lure of Heresy (2007), and Why the Romantics Matter (2015). Correspondence is both personal and professional in nature, with correspondents including his family, academic colleagues, and library and archives staff. Most of the photographs in the papers are personal in nature and subjects include Gay's family and monuments and buildings. Personal papers include a mixture of professional records not related to teaching, research, or writings, as well as personal records, such as financial documents and journals. Newspaper clippings and print outs of interviews with Gay and reviews of his works comprise a significant amount of the personal papers. Materials date from 1865 to 2015.
Gay, Peter, 1923-2015
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in five series: I. Research and teaching files, 1865-2015. II. Writings, 1938-2015. III. Correspondence, 1960-2015. IV. Photographs and slides, 1891-2015. V. Personal papers, 1950-2008.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the research, writing, teaching, and personal life of cultural historian Peter J. Gay. The papers consist of research and teaching files, writings, correspondence, photographs and slides, and personal papers. An extensive part of his research files is the work he completed on Sigmund Freud while writing Sigmund Freud: A Life for Our Time (1998). His teaching files are mainly lecture drafts and also include outlines and notes. His research files are organized both by topic area or writing project; his teaching files are exclusively by topic area.
Gay's writing files contain more of his later articles, book manuscripts, and lectures than his earlier works. Of the books he wrote, only three of them are documented in detail in the papers: My German Question (1998), Modernism: The Lure of Heresy (2007), and Why the Romantics Matter (2015). Writings on Freud in the papers are limited to a handful of articles and lectures and include drafts of an unpublished Encyclopedia Britannica article.
Correspondence is both personal and professional in nature. Correspondents include members of Gay's family, friends, researchers and academics, archivists and librarians at institutions Gay was planning on visiting, publishers, and university and/or conference staff extending invitations to Gay to speak. Most of the photographs in the papers are personal in nature, with subjects being Gay's family or monuments and buildings from vacations. Some photographs from professional event are also present.
Personal papers include a mixture of professional records not related to teaching, research, or writing, and include minutes from professional association meetings and business directories, as well as personal records, such as financial documents and notebooks used as journals. A significant amount of the personal papers also includes newspaper clippings and print outs of interviews with Gay and reviews of his works. Materials date from 1865 to 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Estate of Peter J. Gay, 2015.
Biographical / Historical
Peter Gay was born Peter Joachim Fröhlich on June 20, 1923 in Berlin, Germany. His father, Moritz, owned a glassware business. The Fröhlich family was of Jewish ancestry and lived in Germany during the early years of the Nazi regime. By 1938, Moritz lost the glassware business and Peter was no longer allowed to attend school. In 1939, the family received visas to emigrate to Cuba and they were on the last ship from Nazi Germany allowed into Havana. They moved to the United States in 1941 and changed their last name to Gay, an English translation of Fröhlich, for ease of pronunciation by Americans. Gay attended the University of Denver and graduated in 1946. He earned his master's degree in history in 1947 and a doctorate in political science in 1951, both from Columbia University. Gay taught political science at Columbia from 1947 until 1956, when he switched to the history department. He joined the Yale University history faculty in 1969 and remained at Yale until his retirement in 1993.
While his original academic work focused on labor history and socialist history in political science, Gay transitioned into cultural history scholarship and became renowned for his work on the Enlightenment and 20th century European thought. His texts on Enlightenment figures include Voltaire's Politics (1959) and the two volume The Enlightenment: An Interpretation (1966, 1969). The first volume, subtitled The Rise of Modern Paganism won the National Book Award for History and Biography in 1967. Gay subsequently studied Freud and psychoanalysis, including undergoing psychoanalysis and training as a psychoanalyst at the Western New England Institute for Psychoanalysis. This produced several works including the biography Sigmund Freud: A Life for Our Time (1988). After his retirement, he continued to research and write books, including Modernism: The Lure of Heresy (2007) and Why the Romantics Matter (2015). Other works include his memoir My German Question: Growing Up in Nazi Berlin (1998).
Gay married sociologist Ruth Slotkin in 1959. They raised three daughters from his wife's previous marriage and Gay had seven step-grandchildren. Peter Gay died on May 12, 2015 in New York, New York.
Biographical information is drawn from Richard J. Evans, "Peter Gay Obituary," The Guardian, May 24, 2015, https://www.theguardian.com/books/2015/may/24/peter-gay and William Grimes, "Peter Gay, Historian Who Explored Social History of Ideas, Dies at 91," New York Times, May 12, 2015, https://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/13/arts/peter-gay-historian-who-explored-social-history-of-ideas-dies-at-91.html?_r=0
Europe -- Intellectual life -- 20th Century; Judaism and culture; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Modernism (Art); Modernism (Literature); Psychoanalysis; Romanticism; Gay, Peter, 1923-2015; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939; Yale University -- Faculty
- Research and teaching files, 1845-2015; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I comprises materials Gay used for researching his academic and instructional writings. The majority of his research files consist of articles, offprints, and newspaper clippings that he filed together by either subject area or by title of the article or book he was researching. Especially notable is research that Gay performed on Sigmund Freud while writing Sigmund Freud: A Life for Our Time (1988). This includes articles, book chapters, copies of relevant archival materials, notes, annotated and edited drafts, and related correspondence. There is also a significant amount of research related to Modernism: The Lure of Heresy (2007). Some drafts of his writings are included in this series as they were interfiled with research materials. Please view Series II, Writings, for the bulk of his drafts.
  Gay's teaching files are filed by topic and mainly consist of outlines, drafts, and final copies of his lectures. There are some course syllabi and lecture slides. Some student work is also present. In many cases, folder topics are specific people he lectured on, rather than courses he taught.
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged under two headings, Research files and Teaching files, and alphabetically therein.
  - Research files
    - General, 1908-2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Architecture, 1893-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Art and art history, 1976-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - L'Athenaeum Francais (copies), 1852-1856 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Australian art, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clippings from the Nation, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Colleagues' reprints, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cultural revolution, 1978-1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Dance, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Deutschen Literaturarchivs, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Dissertation abstract by Newt Gringrich, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Douglas, Lawrence, and George, Alexander, "Freud's Phonographic Memory and the Case of the Missing Kiddish Cups", 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Dutch art, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - E.B [?] correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Fichtner, Gerhard, "Freud and the Hammerschlag Family: A Formative Relationship", 2010 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Freud, Sigmund
      - General, 1886-2006 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
      - Abraham papers, Circa 1986- Circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
      - Cases, Circa 1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Copyright holders, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Freud-Ferenczi, Circa 1981- Circa 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Freud-Grinker correspondence, 1933-1936 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Freud-Jones correspondence, Circa 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      - Freud Museum, 1929-1986 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
      - Freud-Rank correspondence, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Jones Papers, 1953-1955; Circa 1980-Circa 1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Freud, Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University materials, Circa 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - New York Psychoanalysis | Brill Library, Circa 1928- Circa 1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Offprints, 1949-1987 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
      - Personal correspondence, 1884-1885 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Research correspondence, 1981-1987 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
      - Second edition research, 1989-1992 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
    - García Márquez, Gabriel, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - George Eliot and blackmail, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Great Histories, 1978-1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "Hidden Agendas" article, 1955-1988 (Box 4, Folder 7, Box 5, Folder 1)
    - History, 1990-2003 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "Jews in Germany at Home", 1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Johnson, Terry. Hysteria, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Jones Co, Eugene, 1969-2015 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Landauer, Carl. "The Ambivalence of Power: Launching the American Journal of International Law in the era of Empire and Globalization", 2007 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Levi (copies), 1861-1975 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
    - Liber | Mottos, Circa 2006 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - "The Liberal Temperment", 2003-2007 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Liberalism, 1865-2006 (Box 5, Folder 11-12, Box 6, Folder 1-4)
    - Liberalism, philosophy, 1948-2000 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Library of Congress notes and copies, 1912-1986 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
    - Liebermann (copies), 1896-1904 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Literature and literary theory, 1977-2003 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Seven | Camera works ( Maya Deren and the American Avant Garde ), 2001 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Loewenberg, Peter. "Nixon, Hitler, and Power: An Ego Psychological Study", 1986 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Mechanization, 1976-2002 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Modernism: The Lure of Heresy
      - General, 1931-2002 (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
      - Art, 1972-2006 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Classics, 1985-2003 (Box 7, Folder 7-8, Box 8, Folder 1-2)
      - Gravediggers, 2001-2002 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - "Life After Death" chapter, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Literature, 1903-2005 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Music, 1981- Circa 2004 (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
      - "Music and Dance" chapter, 1965-2005 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Prose, 1989-2005 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Munich, Undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Music, 2002-2003 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Newsweek: "How U.S Catholics View their Church", 1967-03-20 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Notecards with citations, Circa 1975- Circa 2007 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Notes on "The Open Hand: Essay on Le Corbusier", Circa 1977 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Offprints
      - General, 1938-2005 (Box 9, Folder 2-7)
      - Art, 1975; 2001-2005 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Clive, John, "Peter and the Wallah: From Kinsfolk to Competition", 1981 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - German language, 1996-2003 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - German, 19th century, Circa 1880- Circa 1915; 1974 (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Liberalism, 1976-2005 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Modernism, 1995-2003 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Realism, 1888-1890; 1972 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Research notes, Circa 2001- Circa 2003 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Romanticism/confrontation, 1981-1997 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Ross, Alex. "The Unforgiven: Why the Wagner Problem won't go away", 1998-08-10 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Schack (copies), 1845-1902; 1969-1974 (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
    - Schack, notes, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Sigmund Freud and His Impact on the Modern World, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Schnitzer diary, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Shaw, George Bernard, 1973-1977 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Social Control, 1975-1990 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Société des Gens de Lettres, 1938- Circa 1989 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - "Spirit of Letter," used notes, 1872-1994 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
    - State University of New York at Binghamton, forward to the Freud catalog, 1988-1995 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - "Travail of L. Cult", 1978-1983 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Teaching files
    - Aristotle, Circa 1989 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Augustine, 1927-1965 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Bacon, Francis, Circa 1939 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Calvin, John, 1980- Circa 1989 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - "Freud Reads Goethe", Circa 1980- Circa 1989 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Gibbon, Edward, Circa 1980- Circa 1989 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Hobbes, Thomas, Circa 1989 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Hume, David, 1956- Circa 1989 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Impressionism, Circa 1969- Circa 1999 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Machiavelli, Niccolo, Circa 1989 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Mill| Nietzsche| Freud, Circa 1969- Circa 1999 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Montaigne, Michel de, Undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Nietzsche, Frederic, Circa 1969- Circa 1999 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Pascal, Blaise, Circa 1980- Circa 1989 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Plato, 1984-1989 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Rome-Cicero, Tacitus, Circa 1969- Circa 1993 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Rousseau, Jean-Jacques, Circa 1980- Circa 1989 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Shakespeare, William, 1987-1989 (Box 12, Folder 12, Box 13, Box 1)
    - Slides for two lectures on Jews in Germany, Undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Student thesis, "Professionalisation of Jewish Cantors" by Esther Schmidt, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Sublimation, 1969-2000 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Symbolism, Circa 1969- Circa 1999 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Thucydides, Circa 1989 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Poennies, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Voltaire, Circa 1989 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Writings, 1938-2015; Series II
  Series II comprises drafts and outlines of Gay's writing projects. About half of the series consist of shorter pieces like articles and lectures. Book drafts are also included, primarily from Modernism: The Lure of Heresy (2007) and Why the Romantics Matter (2015). Both drafts are subdivided by chapter, book section, or time frame. Background materials for My German Question, including physical objects photographed for the book, are within this series. For family photographs also used in the book, see Series IV, Photographs and slides.
  Series II is arranged alphabetically.
  - General drafts and notes, Circa 1975- 2001 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - General writings, Circa 1978- 2003 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Articles
    - General, Circa 2000- circa 2010 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - "Against Postmodernism", 1999 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - "Carl Becker's Heavenly City", 1957-06 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Countertransference, 1959-1977 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica manuscript on Freud, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - "Freud as Jew", Circa 1988- circa 1989 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - "Freud's Identity" partial draft, Circa 1980- circa 1985 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Hanslick, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - "The History of History", Circa 1970- circa 1979 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Jewish Origins of Psychoanalysis, Circa 1980- circa 1989 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Levi, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 13-14)
    - "Libby" Draft, 2002-2003 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - "The Liberal Temperament", Circa 2003 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - May, Karl, 1962 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - "Menschen Leben Mit Vielen Identitäten", 1999-11-23 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Modernism | Classics, 1993-2002 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Nietzsche, 1983-1999 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - "Philosophy of History", Circa 1965- circa 1979 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - "Pleasure and Books", Circa 1994 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Postmodernism, 2006 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - "Surprise! Jews in Modern Art", Circa 2004 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - "Toward a New, New History", Circa 1980- 1989 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - "Vulgarians at the Gate", Circa 1999- circa 2015 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Books
    - Imperial Culture, outline, 1975-1978 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - "Love and Work" partial draft, Circa 1960 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Modernism: The Lure of Heresy
      - "Art for Artists' Sake" chapter, Circa 2003- circa 2007 (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - Bibliographical essay, Circa 2009 (Box 15, Folder 12)
      - Deleted material, Circa 2003-circa 2007 (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - Digital files, Circa 2003-circa 2007 (Box 36)
        Conditions Governing Access
        The computer files are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu. The request should outline the scope and purpose of the research project, why the researcher believes the material is relevant to their project, and contact information. If possible the request should also include a list of specific material of interest including collection, box, and folder numbers (or folder descriptions if folders are not numbered). The review may take several weeks.
      - Early drafts, Circa 2003-circa 2007 (Box 15, Folder 14)
      - Endnotes and footnotes, Circa 2003-circa 2007 (Box 15, Folder 15)
      - Full draft, Circa 2003-circa 2007 (Box 15, Folder 16-17, Box 16, Folder 1-2)
      - "Hard Times" (early draft), 2007 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - "Music and Dance: The Liberation of Sound" chapter, Circa 2007 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Outlines, 2001-2006 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - "Painting and Sculpture: The Madness of the Unexpected" chapter, 2007 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - "Professional Outsiders" chapter, 2007 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Prose and poetry chapter, early drafts, 1988-2003 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - "Prose and Poetry: Intermittences of the Heart" chapter, Circa 2007 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - My German Question, 1938-1997 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - My German Question, documents, Circa 1936-1940 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Nervousness: A Short Anthology, Circa 1965- circa 1999 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Why the Romantics Matter
      - "Art for Artists Sake" Chapter, Circa 2015 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - "The Beethoven Decades" Chapter, Circa (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - Bibliography and chapter endnotes, Circa 2015 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Deleted Material, Circa 2015 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Endnotes, 2013- Circa 2015 (Box 17, Folder 3-4)
      - Epilogue, Circa 2015 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - "Middlemen as Pedagogues" Chapter, Circa 2007 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Outlines, 2006-2007 (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Partial full draft, Circa 2015 (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - Preface, Circa 2015 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - "The Re-enchantment of the World" chapter, Circa 2015 (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - "The Re-enchantment of the World" early draft, Circa 2015 (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Romantic psychology chapter, Circa 2015 (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - Table of Contents and Preface, Circa 2015 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Lectures
    - General, 2015 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - "A Century of European Cultural History", 1983-1991 (Box 17, Folder 15-16)
    - "A Godless Jew Revisited" (lecture at the American Psychiatric Association), 1990; 1 (Box 32)
      Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
    - Class of 1946 address, University of Denver, 1996 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - "Eating People is Wrong: Reflections on the Liberal Temper", 2004 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - "Eros: Veiled and Naked", Circa 1999 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Ex-Germans, Circa 2005- circa 2015 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Freud, Circa 1985-circa 1990; 1 (Box 33)
    - "Freud's Jewish Identity", Circa 1980- circa 1989 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Gartenlaube, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Gunter Grass, Northwestern University, 2003-2007 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - "It is Better to Give than Receive: German Jews in German High Culture, Circa 1995- circa 2015 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - John Dippel Lecture, 1997-02-20; 1 (Box 34)
    - Keynote speeches, Unidentified, Circa 2000- Circa 2015 (Box 18, Folder 3-4)
    - Language, Literature and Society Symposium at Loyola College, Maryland, 2005-2007 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - "Modernism in Exile", 2003 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - "On the Future of Psychoanalysis", Circa 1996- 1999 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Philosophy of history, 1982-09-23; 1 (Box 35)
    - "The Psychoanalytic Historian: A Utopian Program", Circa 1985- circa 1999 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Romanticism, Circa 2000- circa 2015 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - "Stories: Reflections on the Historian's Responsibility", 1971-07 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - "The Task of Cultural History", Circa 1989- circa 1992 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - "Towards a New, New History", Circa 1962- circa 1970 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - "Unfinished Business", Circa 2006 (Box 18, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1960-2015; Series III
  Series III comprises personal and professional correspondence to and from Peter Gay. In most cases, his correspondence was filed by whether it was answered or not answered rather than by any specific subject or correspondent. In some cases, he filed by topic.
  Series III is arranged alphabetically.
  - General, 1961-2015 (Box 19, Folder 1-11, Box 20, Folder 1-4)
  - Addresses, 2003-2006 (Box 20, Folder 5-6)
  - Answered mail, 1960-2006 (Box 20, Folder 7-12)
  - Beck, Wolfang, 1995 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Berlioz talk, 2000 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Brown Univeristy, 1993 (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Celebration of Sigmund Freud in Berlin, 2006-05-07 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence to answer, 2003-2008 (Box 21, Folder 1-5)
  - Eissler, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1994-1995 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Family correspondence, 1948-1960 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Figlio-Essex, 1994-1996 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Freud research and leads, 1985-1987 (Box 21, Folder 10-11)
  - German Institutions, 1971-2006 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Modernism, 2006-2007 (Box 22, Folder 1)